[Music]
arsenic is a carcinogenic heavy metal
and the major mechanism of
arsenic-related damage appears to be
oxidative stress it's the
arsenic-induced accumulation of free
radicals that can kill off cells and
damage our dna
and then the double whammy is that it
may disrupt our body's ability to repair
our dna once it's damaged
well if the damage is oxidation what
about eating an antioxidant rich food
such as the spice turmeric which
contains an antioxidant pigment known as
curcumin
as anyone familiar with my videos can
attest numerous clinical trials have
suggested therapeutic efficacy against a
variety of human diseases including
cancer diabetes alzheimer's and
inflammatory bowel joint lung skin and
eye diseases
in terms of protection against heavy
metals
they suggest turmeric may both help
scavenge the radicals as well as chelate
or bind up heavy metals complete with a
fancy colorful diagram but it's all just
theory
until you put it to the test
unfortunately until recently the tests
were like this where you can see if
curcumin can protect against heavy metal
induced oxidation in pureed rat brains
why can't he just give some turmeric to
people it's not like there aren't
millions of people out there who've been
exposed to arsenic and could use some
help
and what became the greatest chemical
disaster in human history so-called tube
wells were installed in bangladesh to
provide clean water
unicef meant well
too bad they didn't test the water for
arsenic
people started showing up with feet that
looked like this and as many as one in
10 in some parts of the country will now
go on to die from cancers caused by the
arsenic exposure
this allowed the medical community to
document all sorts of interesting
cancers
but why not give them something that may
help
like turmeric curcumin
after determining the extent of dna
damage 50 of volunteers were randomly
selected and prescribed curcumin
capsules blended with little black
pepper compound and the other half were
given a placebo
here's the amount of dna damage that was
found in the curcumin and placebo groups
of arsenic exposed individuals before
the study started
compared to the dna damage found in a
control group of individuals not exposed
to arsenic which remained the same
throughout the study
now they wanted to establish a baseline
in the arsenic exposed group so they
waited for three months to start the
study and indeed the dna damage remained
stable
then for three months they proceeded to
give them the curcumin or the placebo
the placebo didn't do much but within
the first month you could see the
curcumin working and by the third month
the dna damages the curcumin treated
arsenic group was no worse than those
who hadn't been exposed to arsenic at
all that's
amazing
the curcumin had an effective role in
the regression of dna damage
yes it's an excellent antioxidant agent
but what they found subsequently is that
the curcumin undid
the arsenic crippling of our dna repair
enzymes so both help prevent the damage
and facilitate repair
thus curcumin may be a useful modality
for the prevention of arsenic-induced
cancer development
of course you have to make sure the
turmeric itself isn't contaminated with
heavy metals all those poor kids in
bangladesh it's not one thing it's
another and it's not just kids in
bangladesh nearly a quarter of spices
purchased in boston had lead in them
it's not just a matter of buying us
versus foreign brands as the lead levels
were not found to be statistically
significantly different
how about just eating antioxidant rich
fruits and vegetables
the reason we care about dna damage is
that we care about cancer
what if you measure the beta-carotene
levels in people exposed to arsenic who
went on to develop cancer compared to
those who got exposed to the same amount
of arsenic but didn't get cancer
beta-carotene is like a proxy for
healthy fruit and vegetable intake the
way you get high levels in your blood is
you eat lots of healthy foods like
greens and sweet potatoes
compared to those with low levels
those with high levels of beta-carotene
in their blood had
lower odds
of getting arsenic-induced cancer a
hundred times lower odds
so if you're gonna eat rice why not some
rice with some sweet potatoes on top
[Music]
foreign